Room E.01 Helmholtzstr. 18 89081 Ulm, Germany

Lukas Niebel

PhD Student at Ulm University

+49 157 83632890 lukasniebel.github.io lukas.niebel@uni-ulm.de

I am a PhD student at Ulm University under the supervision of Prof. Rico Zacher. My research concerns the regularity theory of linear and nonlinear kinetic partial differential equations. I am interested in a precise L^p -solution theory for linear kinetic PDE and in understanding a priori estimates for weak solutions of kinetic PDE. The goal is to apply these results to nonlinear kinetic PDEs such as the Boltzmann and Landau equations. Preprints of all publications are available on arXiv.

LIST OF PUBLICATIONS

Kinetic maximal L^p -regularity with temporal weights and application to quasilinear kinetic diffusion equations 01/2022 with Rico Zacher, Journal of Differential Equations, 307, p. 29–82, link to the article.

Kinetic maximal $L_n^p(L^p)$ -regularity for the fractional Kolmogorov equation with variable density Nonlinear Analysis, 214, link to the article.

01/2022

Kinetic maximal L^2 -regularity for the (fractional) Kolmogorov equation

04/2021

with Rico Zacher, Journal of Evolution Equations, 21, p. 3585–3612, link to the article.

EDUCATION

PhD student since 04/2019

Ulm University

- Working title: Analytic aspects of kinetic partial differential equations
- · Advisor: Prof. Dr. Rico Zacher
- My studies are funded by a graduate scholarship (grant number 1902 LGFG-E).

M.Sc. Mathematics 03/2018 - 03/2019

Ulm University

- Thesis: Kolmogorov equations Well-posedness, regularity, asymptotics and Harnack inequalities
- Grade: 1.0 with distinction, awarded for best graduation
- During my master's studies, I focused on Analysis by taking courses on the calculus of variations, evolution equations, functional calculus, partial differential equations and optimal transport. This was supported by courses in applied mathematics, such as numerical finance, as well as a series of lectures on econophysics.

B.Sc. Mathematics 10/2014 - 02/2018

Ulm University

- Thesis: Long-time behaviour of Markov chains by discrete functional inequalities and entropic Ricci curvature
- Grade: 1.1 with distinction, awarded for best graduation

Abitur, Joachim-Hahn-Gymnasium Blaubeuren

06/2014

Junior studies in mathematics, Fernuniversität Hagen and PfH Göttingen

04/2013 - 09/2014

WORKING AND TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching assistant since 03/2020

University of Applied Sciences Neu-Ulm (HNU)

Neu-Ulm, Germany

 Design and supervision of a supplementary course on statistics and applications for first-year students with an emphasis on programming in R.

Pre-doctoral fellow 04/2019 - 10/2019Ulm University Ulm, Germany

· Head of teaching assistants for Analysis 1.

Creation and presentation of exercises supplementary to the lectures, responsible for the student assistants. Assisting in the creation and correction of the exams.

• Organisation of the Trainingscamp, a yearly event for first-year students to refresh their mathematical skills.

Teaching assistant 10/2017 - 03/2019Ulm University Ulm, Germany

Head of teaching assistants for Analysis 2, Dynamical Systems and Elements of Functional analysis.

Working student 03/2015 - 03/2019

Daimler AG Research & Development

Ulm, Germany

• Statistical Analysis with Matlab and Excel.

Supervising the operation of a quasi-static tension-compression testing machine.

Student assistant 10/2015 - 09/2017Ulm University Ulm, Germany

• Tutor for the Mathlabs Analysis 1 and Analysis 2.

AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

Travel grant by the ProTrain		
	U Mobility-Programm, Ulm University (1000 €)	06/2022
Master graduation award "A	Absolventenpreis M.Sc. Mathematik Uni Ulm 2020" for the best graduation	04/2022
Graduate scholarship grante	ed by the State of Baden-Wuerttemberg, Germany (grant number 1902 LGFG-E)	since 11/2019
Bachelor graduation award	"Absolventenpreis B.Sc. Mathematik Uni Ulm 2018" for the best graduation	05/2018
Ferry Porsche Award and gra	aduation award of the "Deutsche Physikalische Gesellschaft"	06/2014
VOLUNTEER WORK		
	ncil of PhD students at Ulm University	since 02/2021
	sts of doctoral students in university committees, e.g. for the change of	
9	nce 12/2021, chair of the council PhD students.	
	lty council for Mathematics and Economic Sciences of Ulm University	since 02/2020
	udent Council Mathematics	07/2017 - 03/2019
 For example member of 	the appointment committee for a professorship in "Stochastics".	
OTHER SCIENTIFIC ACTIV	ITIES	
•	inar "Mathematisches Kolloquium" at Ulm University	since 03/2020
	h researchers are invited to give a talk accessible to a broad audience.	/
	sshop for PhD students in mathematics at Ulm University	06/2022
	ipants, funding (approx. 2000 €) acquired by the StuVe Ulm University.	
	the workshop of the 25th Internetseminar	03/2022 - 06/2022
	tion in $L^p(\mathbb{R}^{2n})$ – Semigroup, spectrum, maximal regularity?	/
	vril Imbert, École normale supérieure Paris, one week	11/2021
	hool "COLLAB – Collaboratory for Global Sustainability 2021", Toronto/Ulm	10/2021
TALKS AND POSTERS		
Poster — When Kinetic Theory meets Fluid Mechanics, ETH Zürich		07/2022
Poster — 11th Summer school on "Methods and Models of Kinetic Theory", Pesaro		06/2022
Poster — Frontiers in analysis of kinetic equations, INI Cambridge		01/2022
Talk — Nonlinear Evolution Equations and Approximations, Essen		07/2021
Talk — Oberseminar Analysis, Ulm		03/2021
	nalysis and Applied Mathematics, Münster	02/2021
ATTENDED CONFERENCE		
2nd IST Austria Summer School in Analysis and PDEs, IST Austria		07/2022
When Kinetic Theory meets Fluid Mechanics, ETH Zürich		07/2022
25th Internetseminar "Spectral Theory for Operators and Semigroups", Agropoli		06/2022
11th Summer school on "Methods and Models of Kinetic Theory", Pesaro		
		06/2022
Oxbridge PDE Conference, C		05/2022
Oxbridge PDE Conference, C Frontiers in the Interplay Be	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh	05/2022 04/2022
Oxbridge PDE Conference, C Frontiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh v tutorial, INI Cambridge	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022
Oxbridge PDE Conference, C Frontiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new Frontiers in analysis of kinet	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh v tutorial, INI Cambridge tic equations, INI Cambridge	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022 01/2022
Oxbridge PDE Conference, C Frontiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new Frontiers in analysis of kinet Deep Learning and partial d	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh v tutorial, INI Cambridge tic equations, INI Cambridge lifferential equations, INI Cambridge	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022 01/2022 07/2021
Oxbridge PDE Conference, C Frontiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new Frontiers in analysis of kinet Deep Learning and partial d Recent advances in Gradien	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh v tutorial, INI Cambridge tic equations, INI Cambridge lifferential equations, INI Cambridge vt Flows, Kinetic Theory, and Reaction-Diffusion Equations, Vienna	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022 01/2022 07/2021 03/2021
Oxbridge PDE Conference, Contiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new Frontiers in analysis of kinet Deep Learning and partial decent advances in Gradien Kinetic Equations: from Moc	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh v tutorial, INI Cambridge tic equations, INI Cambridge lifferential equations, INI Cambridge vt Flows, Kinetic Theory, and Reaction-Diffusion Equations, Vienna deling Computation to Analysis, CIRM Marseille	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022 01/2022 07/2021 03/2021 03/2021
Oxbridge PDE Conference, Contiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new Frontiers in analysis of kinet Deep Learning and partial decent advances in Gradien Kinetic Equations: from Moc Winterschool on Analysis an	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh v tutorial, INI Cambridge tic equations, INI Cambridge lifferential equations, INI Cambridge of Flows, Kinetic Theory, and Reaction-Diffusion Equations, Vienna deling Computation to Analysis, CIRM Marseille and Applied Mathematics, Münster	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022 01/2022 07/2021 03/2021 03/2021 02/2021
Oxbridge PDE Conference, Corontiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new Frontiers in analysis of kinet Deep Learning and partial decent advances in Gradien Kinetic Equations: from Moc Winterschool on Analysis an Gradient flows and variatior	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh of tutorial, INI Cambridge tic equations, INI Cambridge lifferential equations, INI Cambridge of Flows, Kinetic Theory, and Reaction-Diffusion Equations, Vienna deling Computation to Analysis, CIRM Marseille and Applied Mathematics, Münster all methods in PDEs, Ulm University	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022 01/2022 07/2021 03/2021 03/2021 02/2021 11/2019
Oxbridge PDE Conference, Contiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new Frontiers in analysis of kinet Deep Learning and partial decent advances in Gradien Kinetic Equations: from Moc Winterschool on Analysis and Contient flows and variation PDE/Probability Interactions	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh v tutorial, INI Cambridge tic equations, INI Cambridge lifferential equations, INI Cambridge of Flows, Kinetic Theory, and Reaction-Diffusion Equations, Vienna deling Computation to Analysis, CIRM Marseille of Applied Mathematics, Münster of Interval in PDEs, Ulm University of Particle Systems, Hyperbolic Conservation Laws, CIRM Marseille	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022 01/2022 07/2021 03/2021 03/2021 02/2021 11/2019
Oxbridge PDE Conference, Corontiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new Frontiers in analysis of kinet Deep Learning and partial decent advances in Gradien Kinetic Equations: from Moco Winterschool on Analysis and From Boco Porobability Interaction Porabolic Evolution Equation	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh of tutorial, INI Cambridge tic equations, INI Cambridge differential equations, INI Cambridge of Flows, Kinetic Theory, and Reaction-Diffusion Equations, Vienna deling Computation to Analysis, CIRM Marseille and Applied Mathematics, Münster anal methods in PDEs, Ulm University as: Particle Systems, Hyperbolic Conservation Laws, CIRM Marseille ans, Harmonic Analysis And Spectral Theory, Bad Herrenalb	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022 01/2022 07/2021 03/2021 02/2021 11/2019 10/2019
Oxbridge PDE Conference, Corontiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new Frontiers in analysis of kinet Deep Learning and partial decent advances in Gradien Kinetic Equations: from Moc Winterschool on Analysis and Gradient flows and variation PDE/Probability Interaction Parabolic Evolution Equation Non Standard Diffusions in I	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh of tutorial, INI Cambridge tic equations, INI Cambridge lifferential equations, INI Cambridge of Flows, Kinetic Theory, and Reaction-Diffusion Equations, Vienna deling Computation to Analysis, CIRM Marseille and Applied Mathematics, Münster anal methods in PDEs, Ulm University as: Particle Systems, Hyperbolic Conservation Laws, CIRM Marseille ons, Harmonic Analysis And Spectral Theory, Bad Herrenalb Fluids, Kinetic Equations and Probability, CIRM Marseille	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022 01/2022 07/2021 03/2021 03/2021 11/2019 10/2019 05/2019
Oxbridge PDE Conference, C Frontiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new Frontiers in analysis of kinet Deep Learning and partial d Recent advances in Gradien Kinetic Equations: from Mod Winterschool on Analysis an Gradient flows and variation PDE/Probability Interaction: Parabolic Evolution Equatio Non Standard Diffusions in I	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh of tutorial, INI Cambridge tic equations, INI Cambridge lifferential equations, INI Cambridge of Flows, Kinetic Theory, and Reaction-Diffusion Equations, Vienna deling Computation to Analysis, CIRM Marseille and Applied Mathematics, Münster anal methods in PDEs, Ulm University as: Particle Systems, Hyperbolic Conservation Laws, CIRM Marseille ons, Harmonic Analysis And Spectral Theory, Bad Herrenalb Fluids, Kinetic Equations and Probability, CIRM Marseille	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022 01/2022 07/2021 03/2021 02/2021 11/2019 10/2019
Oxbridge PDE Conference, Oxbridge PDE Conference, Oxfrontiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new Frontiers in analysis of kinet Deep Learning and partial decent advances in Gradien Kinetic Equations: from Moc Winterschool on Analysis and Gradient flows and variation PDE/Probability Interaction Parabolic Evolution Equation Non Standard Diffusions in Evolutionsgleichungen in Ul	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh vitutorial, INI Cambridge life equations, INI Cambridge lifferential equations, INI Cambridge lifferential equations, INI Cambridge life lows, Kinetic Theory, and Reaction-Diffusion Equations, Vienna deling Computation to Analysis, CIRM Marseille life lower management of the life lower life life lower life lower life life lower life life lower life lower life life life life life life life life	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022 01/2022 07/2021 03/2021 03/2021 11/2019 10/2019 05/2019
Oxbridge PDE Conference, Corontiers in the Interplay Be Kinetic Theory: old and new Frontiers in analysis of kinet Deep Learning and partial decent advances in Gradien Kinetic Equations: from Moc Winterschool on Analysis and Gradient flows and variation PDE/Probability Interaction: Parabolic Evolution Equation Non Standard Diffusions in Interpretations on Interpr	etween Probability and Kinetic Theory, Edinburgh of tutorial, INI Cambridge tic equations, INI Cambridge lifferential equations, INI Cambridge of Flows, Kinetic Theory, and Reaction-Diffusion Equations, Vienna deling Computation to Analysis, CIRM Marseille and Applied Mathematics, Münster anal methods in PDEs, Ulm University as: Particle Systems, Hyperbolic Conservation Laws, CIRM Marseille ons, Harmonic Analysis And Spectral Theory, Bad Herrenalb Fluids, Kinetic Equations and Probability, CIRM Marseille	05/2022 04/2022 01/2022 01/2022 07/2021 03/2021 03/2021 11/2019 10/2019 05/2019